<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<body>
		<title>Download Jmol</title>
		<section title="Downloading Jmol">
			<p>The current official release is version $VERSION$.</p>
			<p>It can be downloaded from SourceForge using the following link:
			<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=23629">Jmol downloads page</a>.
      <br/>(Look under the <tt>Jmol</tt> heading for the link whose name ends in <tt>binary.zip</tt> or <tt>binary.tar.gz</tt>, 
	depending on the format you can decompress in your computer.)
			</p>
			<p>
      Some prerelease test versions are also available from time to time (odd-numbered versions like 11.1, 11.3, 11.5). These have not been extensively checked and may have unresolved bugs.
      <br/>(Look under the <tt>Jmol Prerelease Tests</tt> heading for the link whose name ends in <tt>binary.zip</tt> or <tt>binary.tar.gz</tt>, 
	depending on the format you can decompress in your computer.)
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Requirements">
			<p>
	The Jmol web browser applet may run on most browser Java Virtual
	Machines, including the Microsoft and Netscape 4.7* implementations
	of the Java 1.1 JVM. 
	If you are running Microsoft Internet Explorer on the Windows
	operating system you should upgrade to the Sun
	Java Virtual Machine (see below).
      </p>
			<p>
	The standalone Jmol application requires Java 1.4 or higher.
      </p>
			<p>In all cases, if possible, installing the latest Java version from Sun is recommended.
	You can have it installed by visiting
	<a href="http://www.java.com/">www.java.com</a> and following instructions therein.
	</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Installing and Running Jmol">
			<p>Jmol isn't really installed as other programs are, but here is a brief description of how to put it into use:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>To use the Jmol Application (stand-alone program that runs in your computer):
				<ol>
						<li>You only need to extract the <tt>Jmol.jar</tt> file from the downloaded package. 
	Put it in any folder you like (such as <tt>c:\Program files\Jmol\</tt>, or even in <tt>My documents</tt>; the location 
	is not important).
					</li>
						<li>Double-click on the <tt>Jmol.jar</tt> icon (or file) and it will run. Then, use the top menu 
	to open molecular model files. 
					</li>
						<li>For more details, read 
		<a href="http://wiki.jmol.org:81/index.php/Jmol_Application#Installing_Jmol_Application">this page in Jmol Wiki</a>.
					</li>
					</ol><br/>
				</li>
				<li>To use the Jmol Applet (that only runs inside a web browser):
				<ol>
						<li>As a user, you don't need to install or even download Jmol to be able to see web pages that use JmolApplet.
		The necessary applet files will download to your computer automatically at the same time the web page is being downloaded 
	and read. Nothing will be installed in your computer and there are no security concerns.
					</li>
						<li>As a web page author, you need to extract from the downloaded package and put into your webpage folder these files:
		<tt>Jmol.js</tt> and all the files whose name starts with <tt>JmolApplet0</tt> and ends in <tt>.jar</tt>. 
					</li>
						<li> For more details, read 
		<a href="http://wiki.jmol.org:81/index.php/Jmol_Applet#Installing_Jmol_Applet">this page in Jmol Wiki</a>.
					</li>
					</ol>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section title="Subversion Access">
			<p>(For developers only)
			</p>
			<p>
        You can browse the latest source code online or anonymously
        checkout the project contained in the
	<a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a> (SVN)
	repository.
      </p>
			<p>
				<a href="http://jmol.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/jmol/trunk/Jmol">
	  Browse the SVN repository
	</a>
			</p>
			<p>
        To checkout the source code use the following command:
      </p>
			<p>
				<tt>
		svn co https://jmol.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/jmol/trunk/Jmol
	</tt>
			</p>
			<p>
	This will check out to the <code>Jmol</code> subdirectory on your
	system.
      </p>
			<p>
	You can update the source code from withing your Jmol <i>sandbox</i>
	by saying:
	<tt>
	  svn update
	</tt>
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
