<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
	<body>
		<title>Screenshots</title>
		<header>
			<p><i>Click on images to see them full-size.</i></p>
		</header>
		<section title="Small molecules">
			<screenshots>
				<screenshot image="aceticacid.jpg">
          Acetic acid using CPK colors and spacefilled atoms.
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="measurements-1.png">
          A shaded rendering of caffeine, with some measurements shown (distance, angle, dihedral).
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot5.jpg">
          Display of bounding box and axes of coordinates space.
          Note the transparency of the yellow halo around selected atoms.
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="Picture_2.png">
          The electrostatic potential of allene mapped onto a translucent surface.
          <i>(submitted by Nick Greeves)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="water_pmesh.png">
          Two translucent planes (pMesh) illustrating symmetry planes for water molecule.
          <i>(prepared by Bob Hanson)</i>
				</screenshot>
			</screenshots>
		</section>
		<section title="Macromolecules">
			<screenshots>
				<screenshot image="bbdots.jpg">
          A few residues with backbone in blue and vdw dots surface. 
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="hemes.jpg">
          Hemoglobin with backbone trace colored by chain and spacefilled hemes.
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="2hvy.jpg">
          Crystal structure of an H/ACA box RNP from Pyrococcus furiosus (PDB CODE: 2HVY)<br/><b>
						<font color="#afafff">Cbf5p</font>   
          <font color="#aaffbb">Gar1</font>   
          <font color="pink">Nop10</font>   
          <font color="#e6de67">L7AE</font>   
          <font color="#ffaaff">RNA</font></b><br/>
          A nucleotide of the RNA helix is flipped out into the active site formed by the protein complex.<br/>
					<i>(submitted by Wayne Decatur)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot_streptavidin.png">
          Biotin (cpk color, spacefilled) inside its binding pocket in a
          streptavidin subunit (cyan translucent surface) and capped by a portion of
          the neighbour streptavidin subunit (yellow translucent surface).<br/>
					<i>(submitted by Angel Herráez)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot_zincfinger.png">
          A fragment of transcription factor TFIIIA forming three consecutive zinc
          finger motifs (cartoons), bound to a stretch of DNA (spacefilled).
        <i>(submitted by Angel Herráez)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot_hemoglobin.png">
          Highlighting two salt bridges in hemoglobin tetramer (hemo group as sticks
          at bottom-right).
          <i>(submitted by Angel Herráez)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="Thermus_ribosome_1jgo_and_1giy.jpg">
          Eubacterial 70S Ribosome from Thermus thermophilus (PDB CODES: 1jgo and 1giy)<br/>
          On the right is the small subunit and on  the left is the large subunit.<br/>
          In between the subunits: <b>
						<font color="yellow">mRNA</font>
						<font color="pink">A-site tRNA</font>
						<font color="purple">P-site tRNA</font>
						<font color="cyan">E-site tRNA</font></b>
					<i>(submitted by Wayne Decatur)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot_newtranslucency.jpg">
          Illustrates the variable translucency, in preparation for Jmol 11.2.
          <i>(prepared by Bob Hanson)</i>
				</screenshot>
			</screenshots>
		</section>
		<section title="Crystallography">
			<screenshots>
				<screenshot image="crystal-1.png">
          Display of quartz crystal structure, filling 2x2x2 unit cells. The unit cell boundbox is drawn and the unit cell data are shown on upper left.
          <i>(prepared by Bob Hanson)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="zeolite-rho.jpg">
          Network of aluminate-silicate tetrahedra and the volume available for absorption.
          <i>(submitted by Alan Hewat)</i>
				</screenshot>
			</screenshots>
		</section>
		<section title="Orbitals">
			<screenshots>
				<screenshot image="Picture_3.png">
          The 4f-orbitals
          <i>(submitted by Nick Greeves)</i>
				</screenshot>
				<screenshot image="Picture_4.png">
          Cartoon p-orbitals of benzene together with the corresponding translucent molecular orbital.
          <i>(submitted by Nick Greeves)</i>
				</screenshot>
			</screenshots>
		</section>
		<section title="Reactions, vibrations, etc.">
			<screenshots>
				<screenshot image="sn2-distance-anim.gif">
          An S<sub>N</sub>2 reaction animation with the distance
          measured between the chlorine and carbon atoms
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="vibrate.jpg">
          Vibration animation of benzene with vectors shown as yellow arrows and list of vibration frequencies.
        </screenshot>
				<screenshot image="screenshot_pertable.png">
          Periodic table showing atomic, van der Waals and ionic radii for all
          elements with their unique colors.
          <i>(submitted by Angel Herráez)</i>
				</screenshot>
			</screenshots>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
