<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<body>
		<title>Jmol Documentation</title>
		<header>
		</header>
		<section title="Jmol Literature">
			<p>
	 A list of literature describing Jmol can be found at 
			<a href="http://wiki.jmol.org/index.php/Literature">Jmol Wiki</a>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Jmol Technical Notes">
			<p>
			This <a href="../technotes/">document</a> gives technical information 
	about how Jmol is built, particularly with respect to graphics rendering.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Translating Jmol">
			<p>
			Jmol can be translated into your laguage.
			Please, read instructions in
    <a href="http://wiki.jmol.org:81/index.php/Internationalisation">this Wiki page</a>
    and, if you need help, contact the developers team.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Scripting for Jmol">
			<section title="Scripting Documentation">
				<p>
	This <a href="http://www.stolaf.edu/academics/chemapps/jmol/docs">interactive online documentation</a>
	is <b>the</b> reference guide for all commands that form the Jmol scripting language. 
	In addition to an extensive description of all commands and options, it provides 
	excellent demonstrations and examples.
      </p>
			</section>
			<section title="Documentation for the JavaScript Library">
				<p>
	<b>Jmol.js</b> (included in Jmol standard distribution) is a library, written in JavaScript, that can be used to simplify <b>development of 
	web pages</b> that include the JmolApplet. Here is its <a href="../jslibrary/">description and documentation</a>.
				</p>
			</section>
			<section title="Scripting JmolApplet Without Using the JavaScript Library">
				<p>
	<i>Please, note that <a href="../scripting/">these methods</a> are <b>not</b> recommended. 
	You should use them only if you are	experienced and you know precisely what you need. 
	Particularly, if you are learning how to use JmolApplet and
	scripting, you are encouraged to only use the JavaScript library.</i>
				</p>
				<p>
	Do not insert the JmolApplet using the <code>&lt;applet&gt;</code> tag. With older browsers it
  was possible to put an <code>&lt;applet&gt;</code> tag into the page, so creating an instance of
  the Jmol applet. With newer browsers, particularly those implementing HTML5,
  the <code>&lt;applet&gt;</code> tag is deprecated and should not be used.
  Use the <code>&lt;object&gt;</code> tag instead.
				</p>
			</section>
			<section title="Documentation for Surfaces">
				<p>
	This <a href="surface/">documentation</a>
	describes and compares the different options available in Jmol scripts
	for generating surfaces, either based on the molecule or geometric. 
	It also provides a testing and demonstration page.
		      </p>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Colors Used by Jmol">
			<p>
			This <a href="../jscolors/">document</a> specifies
	which colors Jmol uses for elements, chains, chain direction,
	charge, hydrogen bonds, isosurfaces, positional variability, residues, nucleotides, and
	secondary structure. Also, it describes standard color names in JavaScript and 
	the Netscape 8-bit color palette.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="Atomic and Ionic Radii Used by Jmol">
			<p>
			This <a href="../radii/">document</a> demonstrates, 
	using a 3D periodic table, which radii Jmol uses for elements. 
	Includes atomic, van der Waals and ionic radii.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section title="The Jmol Developers Guide">
			<p>
        The <a href="JmolDevelopersGuide.html">Jmol Developers Guide</a>
	describes Jmol development procedures.
		      </p>
		</section>
		<section title="Official, but not up-to-date, documentation">
			<p>These are official guides for Jmol. They cover the basic functionality of both application and applet, 
	but they have not been updated recently (particularly, for features in version 11 of Jmol). 
	</p>
			<section title="The Jmol Guide">
				<p>
        The <a href="JmolUserGuide/">Jmol Guide</a>
	describes the Jmol application.
      </p>
			</section>
			<section title="The Jmol Applet Guide">
				<p>
        The <a href="JmolAppletGuide.html">Jmol Applet Guide</a>
	describes the Jmol applet.
      </p>
			</section>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
